The fourth section of the Book of Deuteronomy continues Moses’ second farewell address to the Jewish people. Moses begins by urging the people to see (Re’eih, in Hebrew) that G‑d has given them the choice between a life of blessings or one of curses; the choice is theirs.

Moses urged the Jewish people to realize that G‑d gives them the choice between good and evil. Their choice will result either in a life of blessings or one of curses.

Seeing and Believing

[Moses told the Jewish people in G‑d’s Name,] “See, I set before you today a blessing and a curse.” Deuteronomy 11:26
A Divine curse is actually a blessing that is too great to be revealed within our limited world and must therefore be “disguised” as a curse. Our challenge is to see it in this perspective, rather than falling into the trap of becoming angry with G‑d. Thus, pain and negativity exist in order to provide us with free choice. Free choice, in turn, exists in order to enable us to earn the rewards for our choices, so we need not feel unworthy of the blessings that G‑d bestows upon us.

When we recognize that evil exists solely to provide us with the free choice to reject it, our struggle with it becomes much easier.