Moses then told the Jewish people that when they are confronted with a challenge to their faith (such as the prosperity of the wicked or of false prophets), they must remember that G‑d is testing their loyalty and commitment to Him.

Tests of Faith

[Moses told the Jewish people,] “G‑d is testing you to determine whether you really love G‑d with all your heart and all your soul.” Deuteronomy 13:4
We are tested when we witness a lack of the Divine favor that we assume is entitled to those who follow G‑d’s will. Voices from both within and without mock the sufferer’s naïve belief. When G‑d’s presence is hidden in these situations, it simply means that He wishes to grace us with a closer, more intense relationship with Him. In order to preserve our faith in G‑d in the face of situations that test this faith, we have to draw upon deeper levels of commitment than we normally do.

When we pass the test, the test disappears – its purpose having been served – and our formerly deep, hidden connection with G‑d becomes our new normative consciousness.