Moses then taught the Jewish people the law that the sabbatical year cancels loans. He then warned them not to let this fact prevent them from loaning money. Moses then taught the Jewish people that when they dismiss their servants, they must give them a gift. In both cases, they should not worry about the expense, since G‑d will provide them with the means to follow His laws.

Work

[Moses told the Jewish people,] “G‑d will bless you in all that you do.” Deuteronomy 15:18
Although G‑d determines how well we will succeed in our efforts to earn a livelihood, we must not rely solely on His providence, but must put forth reasonable efforts to earn our living.

By the same token, however, we must keep in mind that our efforts are not the direct cause of our material success; they are only a receptacle to contain G‑d’s blessing. In this context, our main concern should be with making ourselves worthy of receiving G‑d’s blessing.