Moses then reviewed with the Jewish people the laws prohibiting mixing wool and linen in garments, the laws governing cases of suspected unchaste behavior, adultery, rape, prostitution, forbidden marriages, conduct in battle, slavery, paying interest on loans, and keeping promises.

Carrying the Day’s First Positive Thought

[Moses told the Jewish people,] “Observe and do whatever issues from your lips.” Deuteronomy 23:24
According to the Code of Jewish Law (the Shulchan Aruch), immediately upon waking up in the morning, our first words should be: “I offer thanks to You, living and eternal King, for You have mercifully restored my soul within me; Your faithfulness is great.”

These, our first words each day, are the issuance of our lips that we should observe and preserve throughout the day. In this way, our gratefulness to G‑d influences our attitudes and conduct throughout the day, infusing them with joy, and similarly affects all those around us.