While pasturing their flocks, Joseph’s brothers plotted how best to eliminate him and the threat they believed he posed. Jacob sent Joseph after them.

Relying on Divine Providence

Before [Joseph] reached [his brothers], they conspired against him. Genesis 37:18
Although they neither intended it nor foresaw it, the brothers’ actions led to Joseph’s eventual rise to power and the survival of Jacob’s entire family. Joseph’s experience vividly demonstrates that whether we realize it or not, everything that happens to us is orchestrated by G‑d for our benefit.

It is therefore foolish and unproductive to be angry with those who appear to be harming us. Although they may indeed be guilty for their actions, they cannot do anything to us that G‑d does not will. Rather, we should learn from Joseph, who repaid his brothers’ evil with kindness, continuing to love them despite their hatred toward him.