Moses blessed the tribe of Joseph that their territory would be abundantly fertile.

The Torah is Sweet

[Moses] said of [the tribe of] Joseph, “May his land be blessed by G‑d with the delicacies of heaven . . . with the delicacies produced by the sun, with the delicacies ripened by the moon . . . with the perennial delicacies of hills, with the delicacies of the land.” Deuteronomy 33:13-16
Moses blessed the tribe of Joseph not only with their material necessities, but with “delicacies,” implying that they will enjoy material abundance. The word “delicacies” is mentioned five times in these verses, corresponding to the five Books of Moses. The Torah is our spiritual food – the nourishment of our souls – so Moses’ blessing to the tribe of Joseph was that the study of the Torah should not only nourish the soul but fill it with delight and pleasure.

This teaches us that during the time that we set aside for studying the Torah, we should forget about all our worldly concerns, in order to be able to immerse ourselves in the Torah totally, thereby enjoying our study of it to the fullest. By so doing, we elicit G‑d’s blessings for material abundance.