After Moses concluded his farewell address, G‑d instructed him to ascend Mount Nebo. G‑d showed Moses prophetically the future of the Jewish people. The Torah then concludes with Moses’ death, informing us that no other prophet would ever arise equaling his level of prophecy.

Sparks of Moses

G‑d showed [Moses] all [that would befall] the Land [of Israel]. Deuteronomy 34:1
The vision of the Jewish people’s future that G‑d granted Moses, up to and including the vision of the final, Messianic Redemption, is a fitting conclusion to the Torah. The Torah was given to humanity in order to enable us to make the world into G‑d’s home. This goal will ultimately be achieved only upon the advent of the final Redemption.

We are taught that a spark of Moses’ soul is present in the leaders of every generation, as well as in each of us as individuals. Thus, Moses’ blessings – which provide us with the means, the impetus, and the vision to fulfill our Divine mission and our destiny, bringing the world to its fullest completion – are channeled through the spiritual leaders of our generation and then through our own selves, as we look to the Torah as our guide to living life to its fullest, to connecting ourselves with G‑d, and to transforming our lives and our world into G‑d’s true home.