In order to renew the covenant between G‑d and the Jewish people upon their entry into the Land of Israel, G‑d instructed the Jewish people to perform an elaborate ritual between Mount Gerizim and Mount Eival.

Daily Renewal

[After describing the covenant-renewal ceremony, Moses told the Jewish people,] “This day you have become a people [bound by covenant] to G‑d.” Deuteronomy 27:9
Our desire for novelty is an intrinsic component of our humanity. Moses therefore told the Jewish people that they become G‑d’s people anew every single day. The covenant between G‑d and the Jewish people was made only once, with the Giving of the Torah at Mount Sinai. But G‑d renews it with each one of us on a daily basis. We should therefore view the daily personal renewal of our relationship with G‑d with as much interest and enthusiasm as if it were the first time – for indeed, it is!