Moses then reassured the Jewish people that despite the threats he had just pronounced, they should be confident in their ability to remain true to G‑d’s covenant and enjoy His protection.

The Key to Success

[Moses told the Jewish people, “You must remain faithful to your covenant with G‑d] in order that you succeed in all you do.” Deuteronomy 29:8
The Hebrew word for “succeed” (taskilu) also means “comprehend.” Thus, this verse implies that by fulfilling G‑d’s commandments, we will “comprehend all that we should do.”

There are many aspects of life in which we struggle to determine how to act in the most spiritually positive manner. By living in accordance with the Torah’s instructions, we become sensitive to G‑d’s will. This, in turn, aids us in comprehending how to act in accordance with G‑d’s will in the context of those areas of life not directly governed by specific commandments.