G‑d told Moses to inform the Jewish people that after they would receive their corrective punishment for their lapses in loyalty to G‑d’s covenant, G‑d would comfort them and punish those who had persecuted them.

Healing the World

[G‑d said,] “I strike and I heal.” Deuteronomy 32:39
The Hebrew word for “strike” (machatzti) is related to the word for “barrier” or “partition” (mechitzah). The sickness that the world presently suffers from is the artificial barrier between the spiritual and the material. The difficulty we experience in trying to sense the spiritual in what we do or in trying to apply our inspiration to our daily lives is the true definition of exile. In the Messianic era, G‑d will heal this split. The dividing barrier will be transformed into a connecting doorway, enabling the spiritual and the material to once again unite. This is how evil will be eliminated in the future: G‑d will be so revealed that evil – the denial of G‑d – will simply cease to exist.

It follows that the way to hasten the Messianic era is by taking care to refine even the lowest aspects of our material lives, infusing them with as much spirituality as we can. By living “messianic” lives in this way, we are doing our part to nullify the exile.