After burying Sarah, Abraham sent his servant, Eliezer, to his brother’s household in Aram to select a suitable wife for Isaac.

G‑d’s Estranged Wives

[Abraham told Eliezer,] “You must go to my land, to my family, and take a wife for my son, Isaac.” Genesis 24:4
The prophets often describe the relationship between G‑d and the Jewish people as that of husband and wife. In this sense, we are all entrusted with a mission comparable to the one that Abraham gave Eliezer – to go out and find those souls that have drifted away and bring them back to G‑d, their “husband.”