Eliezer and his caravan set out for Aram. They arrived at the well outside Haran, the city of Abraham’s brother, Nachor, when the women of the city were drawing water. Eliezer prayed to G d to guide him toward Isaac’s proper match by having her respond generously to his request that she draw water for him and his entourage.

Benevolence

[Eliezer prayed,] “Let it be that the maiden to whom I will say, ‘Please tilt your pitcher so that I may drink,’ and she replies, ‘Drink, and I will also give water to your camels,’ will be the one whom You have designated for Your servant Isaac.” Genesis 24:14
Since G‑d lacks nothing, generosity is the primary way in which He relates to the world. For the same reason, generosity is the natural hallmark of people who feel closely connected to G‑d. In contrast, the hallmark of evil is selfishness. No matter how much an evil person possesses, he remains unsatisfied, so he seeks only to take and never to give.

Eliezer therefore sought a woman for Isaac who would display kindness. When Rebecca went beyond fulfilling Eliezer’s specific request by offering to also water his camels, he understood that she was a G‑dly person and thus a fitting match for the son of Abraham.

By demonstrating kindness to others, we too are “matched” with the most worthy partners – whether soul-mates, friends, business partners, or callings in life.