After chronicling Abraham’s death, the Torah lists the descendants of Ishmael before continuing with the chronicle of Isaac in the next section.

True Love

[Ishmael] dwelled throughout the area [settled by] all his descendants. Genesis 25:18
Literally, the Hebrew original reads: “He fell throughout the area. . . . ” Ishmael was the “fallen” version of Abraham. Abraham personified holy love – love for G‑d and kindness to others. Ishmael personified love in its “fallen” version, an obsessive desire for physicality and sensuality.

In our own lives, it is our task to transform our love and passion for material things – the fallen love of Ishmael – into a holy love for G‑d.