The ninth section of the Book of Deuteronomy continues the description of Moses’ third and final farewell address to the Jewish people. It begins with the account of how Moses went (Vayeilech, in Hebrew) and installed Joshua as his successor, and continues with the account of how Moses wrote down the Torah and commanded the people to assemble every seven years to hear it read in the holy Temple.

Moses informed the Jewish people that this day, the 7th of Adar, was his 120th birthday, and would also be the day that he would die.

Leading a Full Life

[Moses] told [the people], “Today I am exactly 120 years old.” Deuteronomy 31:2
The fact that even Moses’ last year of life was not left unfinished indicates that he lived his life to its fullest, wasting no time and not leaving undone any part of the task with which he was charged.

The fact that Moses’ physical life so perfectly mirrored his spiritual life indicated that he successfully overcame the division between the spiritual and the material: his spiritual perfection was mirrored in this manifestation of physical perfection.

Moses’ life should inspire us to live our own lives to the fullest, the consciousness of our Divine mission permeating every minute and every item in our lives. When we do so, we dissolve the artificial division of the spiritual and the physical, revealing the innate Divinity underlying all reality.