Moses reassured the Jewish people that although he was about to die, G‑d would still and always be with His people. They therefore had nothing to fear from the nations then occupying the Land of Israel, which they were about to enter and conquer.

Whether We Like it or Not!

[Moses told the Jewish people that they can rely on G‑d’s assistance;] “He will neither fail you nor forsake you.” Deuteronomy 31:6
Moses informed us with these words that even if it would occur to us that life would be easier if we were free from both G‑d’s mission and His assistance, such a life is not possible. G‑d will never forsake us. We can never completely silence the inner voice that urges us to discard our infatuation with superficial pursuits and assume the mantle of responsible Jewishness.

For this same reason, we should never feel incapable of fulfilling our Divine mission. The same G‑d who refuses to leave us alone, always prodding us to join Him in perfecting the world, stands at our side to assist us in our efforts to transform the world into His home.