Moses then reviewed with the Jewish people the laws entitling workers in the field or vineyard to partake of the food they are harvesting.

Tasting Rewards

[Moses told the Jewish people, “If you are a hired worker in a vineyard,] you may eat as many grapes as you desire, until you are sated.” Deuteronomy 23:25
Working the grain field and working the vineyard represent the two aspects of our relationship with G‑d. Grain, the basic component of the diet, represents the acceptance of G‑d’s sovereignty and the observance of His commandments. Grapes, a sweet addition to the normal staples of the diet, represent the expression of our relationship with G‑d that goes beyond the letter of the law. When we are spiritually mature enough to feel pleasure and joy in the revelation of G‑dliness, we look to bring awareness of G‑d into all facets of our lives, not only in the ways expressly required by the Torah.

The Torah entitles the workers in the fields and vineyards to partake of the grain and grapes while they work. This teaches us that whether we are relating to G‑d at the basic “grain” level, or have progressed to relating to Him also on the voluntary “grape” level, we will be constantly rewarded by receiving further, greater revelations of divinity and divine beneficence.