Abraham moved from Hebron to Philistia, and when he was 100 years old and his wife Sarah was 90, their son Isaac was born. In the meantime, Hagar’s son Ishmael was showing himself unreceptive to the moral education he was receiving from Abraham. In order to prevent him from being a negative influence on Isaac, Sarah insisted that Abraham banish Hagar and Ishmael. Abraham was reluctant to do so, but G d validated Sarah’s judgment.

Feminine Power

G‑d said to Abraham, “ . . . Whatever Sarah tells you, heed her voice.” Genesis 21:12
The more attuned a prophet is to the affairs of this world, the greater his or her degree of prophecy. Since Abraham was somewhat detached from worldly matters, he could not perceive Ishmael’s true negativity. Sarah, in contrast, was more involved in worldly matters, so she readily was able to perceive Ishmael’s evil. Her prophetic vision was therefore superior to Abraham’s.

Furthermore, we are taught that in the Messianic Era, the feminine aspect of creation will rise above the masculine. Abraham’s and Sarah’s spiritual refinement was so lofty that it enabled them to experience a foretaste of the Messianic Era. For this reason, too, Sarah’s prophetic vision was superior to Abraham’s.

Nowadays, as we approach the Messianic Era, all of us can welcome the flowering of feminine power in the world, acknowledging that women’s more intense experience of physical life grants them a higher level of spiritual insight than that given to men.