The tenth section of the Book of Deuteronomy is composed almost entirely of the Poem of Testimony that G d taught Moses and instructed him to teach the Jewish people. In it, G d bids the Jewish people to hearken (Ha’azinu, in Hebrew) to His words as He reviews their history and informs them of the consequences of their future conduct, whether good or bad.

G‑d called upon both heaven and earth to bear witness to the message He was about to deliver to the Jewish people.

Heaven on Earth

[G‑d said,] “Listen, O heaven . . . Hear, O earth.” Deuteronomy 32:1
G‑d addressed both heaven and earth in order to teach us that we are called upon to harmonize the two. The Torah originates in heaven and consists of G‑d’s vision for the perfection of the world. By spreading the knowledge of the Torah to ourselves and to others, we are bringing heaven down to earth. By reshaping both our own lives and the lives of others in accordance with the Torah’s teachings, we are bringing life on earth up to heaven. When we have made life into “heaven on earth” – reconciling the division between the two – heaven and earth testify how we have fulfilled our mission in life.