G‑d told Moses to inform the Jewish people that He would punish them for their misdeeds, but would nonetheless never forsake them.

G‑d’s Children

[Moses said that G‑d would say,] “They are children who [act] uneducated.” Deuteronomy 32:20
By referring to us as His “children,” G‑d let it be known that He would never sever His relationship with us, and that we can never sever our relationship with Him – just as parents can never sever themselves from their children, and children can never sever themselves from their parents. The relationship between parents and their children is so essential, so strong, that no matter how seriously it may be tested, in the final analysis it will always overcome any behavior that might seem to threaten it.

It is therefore pointless to try to hide or flee from this relationship, and senseless to think that it can ever be forfeited. G‑d’s love for us is infinitely stronger than anything we may have done to weaken it.