fter Moses finished conveying the Poem of Testimony to the Jewish people, he encouraged them to pay heed to all its lessons, as well as to the Torah in general.

G‑d’s Guide to Life

[Moses said to the Jewish people,] “For [the Torah] is not an unrewarding pursuit for you; rather, it is your very life.” Deuteronomy 32:47
The Torah contains all the instructions and lessons that every individual needs in order to live his or her life in accordance with G‑d’s expectations. This is as it should be, for the Torah is the “blueprint” that G‑d used when He created the world. If for some reason we are not sure what the Torah requires of us in a specific situation, we are bidden to consult with qualified Torah scholars, who have learned from their own teachers how to correctly apply the Torah’s wisdom to our lives.

Thus, the literal meaning of this verse is, “For it is not an empty thing from you,” which, the sages of the Talmud tell us, means, “If you find a situation in life that seems empty of – i.e., lacking – the Torah’s direction, it is because of you – i.e., your own inability to apply the Torah’s wisdom to your life.” In such cases, the Torah directs us to seek its application from our teachers and mentors.