The sixth section of the Book of Genesis describes the history (Toledot, in Hebrew) of Isaac and his sons, the righteous Jacob and wicked Esau. It first chronicles their birth, which foretells their future conflict. Esau, the firstborn, sells his birthright to Jacob. The narrative then follows Isaac to Philistia, focusing on his curious project of digging wells. We then see Esau marry. Shortly afterward, Rebecca tricks Isaac into conferring his blessings – and thus the future leadership of the Jewish people – to Jacob rather than to his actual firstborn, Esau. After realizing that Rebecca was correct, Isaac sends Jacob to Aram to marry a daughter of one of his kinsmen.

Isaac and Rebecca had no children for the first 20 years of their marriage. When their prayers were finally answered and Rebecca conceived, she suffered intense pregnancy pain. G‑d informed her that she was pregnant with twins who would be opposites – not only physically, but morally, as well – and that each one’s success in pursuing his path in life would be at the expense of the other’s.

Double Identity

G‑d told her, “Two nations are in your womb; two powers will diverge from within you. The upper hand will pass from one power to the other.” Genesis 25:23
Metaphorically, Jacob and Esau represent the two souls (and their opposing drives) that exist within each of us. We each possess an inner Jacob – i.e., our Divine soul with its G‑dly drives, and also an inner Esau – i.e., our animating soul with its selfish drives. When our Divine soul asserts itself, it weakens the materialistic tendencies of the animating soul.

The Divine soul overcomes the animating soul in the same way that light overcomes darkness. Light does not have to actively exert itself to dispel darkness – darkness simply ceases to exist in the presence of light. Similarly, as soon as we let the holiness and goodness of our Divine souls shine by studying the Torah and observing the commandments, the selfishness of the animating soul disappears.