In addition to his sons Cain and Abel, Adam and Eve had a third son, Seth. One of Seth’s fifth-generation descendants was Enoch, who resisted the degeneration into which the rest of humanity was sinking, and lived a righteous life.

The Largeness of Small Thingי

Enoch walked with G‑d. Genesis 5:22
Enoch was a shoemaker, yet, because of his holiness, his mundane occupation did not distract him from his service of G‑d. On the contrary, we are taught that with every stitch he brought about a further degree of harmony within the spiritual spheres.

We, too, on our own level, can follow in Enoch’s footsteps: We can so infuse our earthly activities with holy intentions that can positively influence the heavens.