PARSHA SUMMARY: The fifth section of the Book of Deuteronomy continues Moses’ second farewell address to the Jewish people. It includes Moses instructions to judges, the king, priests, and the prophets.
DAILY CHUMASH SUMMARY: Moses instructed the Jewish people to appoint judges and sheriffs throughout the Land of Israel to try cases and uphold the law.
DAILY MESSAGE: Personal Judges and Sheriffs

[Moses instructed the Jewish people,] “You must appoint judges and sheriffs for yourself in all your cities.” Deuteronomy 16:18
The Hebrew word for “cities” used here (she’arecha) literally means “gates.” The “gates” of our bodies are our ears, eyes, nose, and mouth, through which stimuli from the external world enter our bodies and our personal world. This verse thus requires us to station “judges and sheriffs” to guard these “gates” against the intrusion of any stimuli that could be harmful to our spiritual health. 