PARSHA SUMMARY: Moses then warned the Jewish people not to listen to false prophets, and reviewed the laws of Cities of Refuge. 

DAILY MESSAGE: Ultimate Refuge

Allegorically, the relative who seeks to avenge the victim’s blood is our own evil inclination. It attempts to trick us into sinning, thereby causing us to suffer some form of spiritual “death,” i.e., a loss of vitality in our spiritual life. 
The study of the Torah is our refuge from our evil inclination, for the holiness of the Torah has the power to neutralize the effect of evil on us.