DAILY CHUMASH SUMMARY: Moses then taught the Jewish people the laws of legal testimony and perjury.

DAILY MESSAGE: G‑d’s True Witnessess

It is the Torah’s position that creation itself testifies to the existence of the Creator. However, the notion that G‑d’s essence is not only beyond our ability to understand but beyond our ability to conceive does not follow from examining the world; this truth must be established by “external” witnesses.
The witnesses to the inconceivable nature of G‑d’s essence are the Jewish people. By studying the Torah and performing G‑d’s commandments, the Jewish people introduce the world to the ineffability of G‑d’s essence.