DAILY CHUMASH SUMMARY: Moses then began to instruct the Jewish people regarding how they were to conduct their conquest of the Land of Israel including the prohibition of destorying any fruit trees.

DAILY MESSAGE: Becoming a Fruit-Bearing Tree

Many people are gifted with superior intelligence or talent, but truly refined emotions are achieved by shedding childlike self-absorption. Fruit-bearing trees provide us with nourishment and delight at their own expense. In contrast, barren trees merely impress us with their stately presence; they may perhaps offer us shade, but they sacrifice nothing in so doing.
Therefore, when we seek instruction and inspiration, we should turn to people who are not only intelligent and talented, but who consistently utilize their gifts for the world’s greater good. 