The name of fifth section of the Book of Genesis is taken from its first words, “The Life of Sarah” (Chayei Sarah in Hebrew), and begins with Sarah’s death and burial. We then follow Abraham’s servant, Eliezer, as he betroths Abraham’s grandniece Rebecca to Abraham’s son Isaac. This account is followed by that of Isaac and Rebecca’s marriage and the closing phases of Abraham’s life: his remarriage to Hagar, his death, and his son Ishmael’s departure from his family and its Divine mission.

When the news reached Sarah that Isaac was nearly sacrificed, the shock of his near loss coupled with the relief of his life being spared was too much for her to bear, and she died. Abraham purchased the Machpeilah Cave and the surrounding field from the local Hittites for her burial grounds in Hebron.

Jewish Destiny

[Abraham said to the Hittites,] “Allow me [to buy] a burial ground among you.” Genesis 23:4
The Machpeilah Cave is the burial site of Adam and Eve, the first human beings; as such, it originally belonged to all humanity. In purchasing it, Abraham articulated G‑d’s intention that the mission originally given to humanity as a whole now be passed on to the Jewish people. By accepting this task, the Jewish people were fundamentally separating themselves from the rest of humanity and assuming the role of its mentors. It is our challenge to recognize this destiny today, as well.