Esau offered to escort Jacob and his family into Canaan, but Jacob declined the favor, promising to visit Esau at his home on Mount Sei’ir.

Maintaining Focus

[Jacob said to Esau,] “Let my master please go on ahead of [me,] his servant . . . [and wait there] until I reach [you,] my master, at Sei’ir.” Genesis 33:14
Jacob alludes here to Esau’s future transformation in the Messianic Era – “until I reach my master [Esau] at Sei’ir.” Jacob’s approach to Esau teaches us how to neutralize the potential hostility of the “Esaus” we encounter during our exile:

If we fall prey to the external comforts of exile and feel subservient to the rulership of “Esau,” our attitude becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy – our exile starts to truly rules us. To neutralize Esau’s power, we must see past the façade of exile to its inner purpose, which is to enable us to prepare the world for the Messianic Era. At that time, “Esau” will be subdued and transformed. By viewing the long adventure of exile as a journey toward Sei’ir, focusing on our ultimate goal, “Esau” is rendered harmless even during the exile.