Included in Moses’ blessings was the promise that the Jewish people would not be conquered by their enemies if they remained faithful to their covenant with G‑d.

For the Entire World’s Sake

[Moses told the Jewish people, “Your enemies] will attack you from one direction, but they will flee from you in seven directions.” Deuteronomy 28:7
Moses did not promise the Jewish people that they would kill their enemies; only that their enemies will be prevented from harming them. From this we see that when the Jewish people follow the Torah’s instructions, it elicits Divine blessing not only for us but for the whole world. Even our enemies are allowed to live peacefully and securely in their own land, and are prevented from harming us in any way.