Exactly one year after the Flood began, the earth was dry enough to be habitable. But Noah was reluctant to leave the ark, for he and the animals had lived in peace and harmony within it. Noah knew that once the animals would leave the ark, they would revert to their naturally aggressive behavior.

Accepting the Challenge

G‑d spoke to Noah, saying “Leave the ark!” Genesis 8:15-16
As we have seen, “entering the ark” is a metaphor for the need to immerse ourselves in Torah study and prayer. However, the true purpose of entering the ark is to leave it. G‑d command us – as He commanded Noah – not to remain in the protective spiritual environment of Torah study and prayer, but to emerge from it, enter the world, and transform the world into G‑d’s home.