When Rebecca gave birth, the first twin to emerge was Esau, although Jacob was actually conceived first. Already as young boys, Esau was drawn toward sensual thrills while Jacob was drawn toward absorbing the wisdom and traditions transmitted by Abraham and Isaac. Understanding that he would be the more faithful steward of the family’s ideals, Jacob offered to trade the right of leadership from Esau for a hot meal, to which Esau readily agreed. After this, when Canaan was plagued by famine, Isaac relocated his family to Philistia, where Rebecca was almost abducted by the Philistine king. Isaac’s righteousness was made evident to everyone when the yield of his crop was miraculously out of proportion to the amount he planted.

The Purpose of Wealth

Isaac sowed grain in that region that year. He reaped a hundredfold, for G‑d had blessed him. Genesis 26:12
It is clear from a close reading of the Torah’s narrative that the patriarchs were astute businessmen. Nonetheless, it is also clear that they engaged in material pursuits solely with the objective of fulfilling G‑d’s will. In this case, Isaac’s true goal in sowing grain was to be able to give charity to the poor, which the Torah stipulates can only be performed with one’s own produce. Like our patriarchs, when our involvement in the pursuit of a livelihood and wealth is similarly motivated, we are blessed with overwhelming success.