Moses then described the experience of receiving the Torah on Mount Sinai.

Eternal Revelation

[Moses told the Jewish people], “G‑d spoke these words . . . with a great voice, not pausing [at all].” Deuteronomy 5:19
One meaning of the expression “not pausing” is that the voice of G‑d at Mount Sinai continued – and continues – to be revealed in the prophecies and teachings of the prophets and sages of each generation. The fact that these prophecies and teachings were not explicitly articulated when the Torah was first given is simply because the world and the Jewish people did not yet require them. They were nonetheless implicit in the original revelation of the Torah.