The kindness and hospitality practiced by Abraham in Hebron stood in stark contrast to the wickedness and inhospitality of the nearby cities of Sodom, Gomorrah, and their neighbors. After the three angels visited Abraham, G‑d informed Abraham that He was going to eliminate these cities, but Abraham pleaded with G‑d on their behalf.

Transcending Our Selves

[Abraham] came forward and said [to G‑d], “Would you obliterate the righteous along with the wicked?!” Genesis 18:23
When Abraham saw that the angels were already headed toward Sodom in order to annihilate it, he realized that he had to go against his naturally kind disposition and that he could not mince words. He had to argue vehemently and demand of G‑d that He annul His decree.

From Abraham’s example we learn that when we are presented with the opportunity to save another person, either physically or spiritually, we must not hesitate. We should immediately do all in our power to come to the person’s aid, even if that means acting in direct opposition to our natural dispositions.