Moses then blessed each tribe separately, emphasizing each one’s unique contribution to the collective mission of the Jewish people. He blessed the tribe of Levi to be worthy of their role as the priests and Levites serving in the holy Temple, and of their charge to teach the Torah to the rest of the Jewish people. He blessed the tribe of Benjamin with the location of the holy Temple. The Temple would eternally be located in Jerusalem, in the territory of the tribe of Benjamin.

Jewish Perpetuity

[Moses blessed the tribe of Levi,] “They will teach [G d’s] ordinances to Jacob [i.e., the Jewish people]. . . . [He blessed the tribe of Benjamin,] “[G‑d’s presence] hovers above him all ‘day’ long [i.e., forever].” Deuteronomy 33:10
Moses’ blessing to the tribe of Levi is meant to inspire all of us to dedicate ourselves to the holy task of promoting Jewish education, to ensuring that every Jew be given the broadest and deepest knowledge of G‑d’s Torah as possible.

By pronouncing the tribe of Benjamin’s blessing immediately after the tribe of Levi’s blessing, Moses teaches us that our dedication to Jewish education must be ongoing and perpetual, and that the Jewish education we promote must be of the type that ensures the perpetual dedication of the Jewish people to G‑d’s Torah and commandments.