Moses then told the Jewish people that they should express their love of G‑d not only as individuals, but as a community.

Two Ways of Loving G‑d

[Moses told the Jewish people,] “If you love G‑d . . . with all your heart and with all your soul . . . ” Deuteronomy 11:13
This verse seems to repeat a similar verse in the previous section of the Torah – but in that verse we are told to love G‑d “with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your might.” Apparently, there are two levels of intensity in loving G‑d: one that includes “with all our might” – i.e., constantly rising above what we consider to be rational or even possible – and one that does not.

This is because we are not all the same. Some of us can maintain a constant awareness of G‑d’s presence in our lives that inspires us to love Him “with all our might,” while some of us cannot maintain this awareness constantly.

Nonetheless, even those of us who can serve G‑d only “with all our heart and all our soul” on an ongoing basis can still rise to serve Him “with all your might” occasionally. In the Messianic future, we will all be able to sustain this high level of Divine awareness. It is for this reason that both verses – both versions of our love of G‑d – have been included in the text of our daily prayers.