The tenth section of the Book of Genesis continues the chronicle of Joseph. It begins two years after (Mikeitz, “at the end of” in Hebrew) Joseph asked Pharoah’s cupbearer to intercede for him. This time it is Pharaoh who dreams – twice – and seeks a qualified interpreter. Joseph interprets Pharaoh’s dreams convincingly as referring to seven coming years of plenty followed by seven years of famine, and this leads Pharaoh to appoint Joseph as viceroy of Egypt. The onset of famine brings Joseph’s brothers to Egypt to buy food that Joseph stored up during the years of plenty. When Joseph sees them, he devises a way to determine if they have abandoned their former hatred of him and are ready to join him in moving the family forward in its Divine mission.

In his first dream, Pharaoh saw seven robust cows emerge from the Nile River, followed by seven lean cows that devoured the seven robust ones. In his second dream, he saw seven healthy ears of grain devoured by seven scrawny ones.

The Price of a Free Lunch

Pharaoh awoke, and perceived that [what he had seen] was a dream. Genesis 41:7
The content of Pharaoh’s dreams differed profoundly from that of Joseph’s. Pharaoh dreamed of animals and produce but not of work. Joseph’s dreams, in contrast, began with the image of work – the brothers gathering sheaves in the field.

This reflects the difference between how G‑d provides sustenance for holy and unholy people. G‑d sustains holy people directly, in deserved reward for their earnest work in aligning themselves with His will. In contrast, unholy people balk at the idea of self-discipline and work; G‑d therefore only sustains them because He has to in order for them to continue to exist. Moreover, sustenance received without effort is flawed goodness, since human nature is such that we do not truly appreciate something gained without effort.

Similarly, when we are tempted to think that we can get by without hard work, we must realize that such notions stem from our unholy side. Likewise, anything we receive “for free” is either flawed or will not endure.