Judah’s display of self-sacrifice for Benjamin convinced Joseph that his brothers had truly repented of their former animosity toward him. He therefore revealed his true identity to them. They were understandably afraid that he would take revenge on them, but Joseph assured them that he viewed the entire episode as Divine providence and did not hold them responsible.

Transcending and Transforming

[Joseph told his brothers,] “G‑d sent me ahead of you to ensure that you survive in [this] land.” Genesis 45:7
It was impressive that Joseph maintained his holiness in exile, but his primary achievement was that he increased holiness in the world, by teaching the Egyptians about G‑d. Joseph’s example gives us the strength to follow in his footsteps, by first remaining immune to the negativity of exile and then by transforming it into holiness.