Moses reminded the Jewish people that when they were at Mount Sinai, G‑d instructed him to share the responsibility of resolving their lawsuits with a system of judges. The people readily accepted this plan, but not for the right reasons: they hoped to be able to influence the rulings of judges of lesser moral caliber than Moses.

The Load Always Fits the Camel

[Moses told the Jewish people at Mount Sinai,] “How can I bear your trouble, your burden, and your strife all by myself?” Deuteronomy 1:12
We are all charged with the same mission as Moses: to educate and lead ourselves – as well as those over whom we have influence – in the ways of the Torah. If we wonder how we can bear such a heavy responsibility, we should recall that when Moses asked G‑d the same question, G‑d immediately provided him with a practical solution. Just as G‑d gave Moses the means to fulfill his mission, G‑d gives us the means and resources to fulfill our Divine mission, regardless of how difficult or overwhelming our responsibilities may appear to be.