Moses then promised the Jewish people that in the future they would indeed enjoy the fulfillment of all of G‑d’s blessings.

Listening to G‑d’s Voices

[Moses told the Jewish people that they would enjoy G‑d’s blessings, for] “You will return [to Him] and listen to His voice.” Deuteronomy 30:8
By “listening to G‑d’s voice,” Moses meant not only that we would obey G‑d, but that we would recognize the inner message within His voice. Our belief that G‑d is good and that all He does is good enables us to thank Him for everything in life – even what seems to be the opposite of good. In the merit of this belief, G‑d will eventually show us how everything He does is truly good.